Finding Aid for Gordon Webber papers, 1936-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gordon Webber papers 1936-1986
Webber, Gordon, 1912-1986.
85434 Aa 2
Author, writer for radio and television programs, and advertising executive; collection includes scripts for radio and television programs, "The Firefighters," "Reflections," and "I Remember Mama"; materials relating to his work in opposition to the Vietnam War; correspondence, speeches, and manuscripts and copies of novels; also photographs and films.
7.5 linear feet
1 phonograph records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from Mr. Webber (Donor no. 5736 ) in 1975, and from his estate in 1987.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gordon Webber (full name Royal Gordon Webber) was born in 1912 to Roy Eugene and Dorothea Boyd Webber, and grew up on a farm in southern Michigan. He attended High School in Linden, MI, and worked for two summers on an automobile assembly line in Flint. Webber attended Johnstown College in Johnstown, ND, and graduated with an AB in 1933, as well as a teaching certificate from Johnstown College in 1934. Webber also attended University of Michigan for graduate school, obtaining a Master's of Art degree in Journalism in 1936.
After graduating from Michigan, Webber worked for the Vick Chemical Co. as a traveling salesman for two years, during which time he traveled through 15 Southern and Midwestern states, selling salve to general and drug stores. Eventually Webber was called to the company's New York office to do advertising and sales promotion work. In 1938 he was hired at the National Broadcasting Company (NBC). Webber worked in the NBC Press Department as a publicity writer until 1940, and from 1940-1942 he worked as a scriptwriter and director in the NBC Radio-Recording division.
Webber served in the United States Navy from 1942-1945, first as a gunnery officer in the Mediterranean and Atlantic Seas (during this time he took part in the invasion at Normandy) and later as a member of the assault transport team in the Pacific during the Japanese occupation.
After the war, Webber returned to the Radio-Recording Division at NBC. He wrote for numerous radio programs, though "The Fire Fighters" and "Reflections" are most well known. Webber worked for NBC until 1948, at which time he left to work for Benton & Bowles, an advertising company in New York City, where he was employed until 1975. In this capacity he wrote for the long-running television show "I Remember Mama."
In the early 1970's Webber became involved in activism opposing the Vietnam War. He was a member of the Corporate Executives Committee for Peace, a business group dedicated to supporting the McGovern-Hatfield bill introduced to the Senate in 1970 (also known as the Amendment to End the War.) Webber was also a member of the group Advertising People Against the War, which prepared television and newspaper advertisements in support of the amendment. "The Endless War: A Safe and Orderly Way Out" was a television news special that Webber produced as part of his work with The Amendment to End the War Committee (which was constituted of 25 US Senators, sponsors of this anti-war legislation before the Senate). "The Endless War" was broadcast on 200 public broadcasting stations in September 1970.
In 1971, Webber also contributed to the anti-war ad campaign "Help Unsell the War." It was begun by Ira Nerken, a junior at Yale University, and gained support from a large section of the advertising community. Interested ad executives were invited to a briefing at Yale University on April 3, 1971, after which time the campaign solicited volunteers from the advertising sector to create anti-war advertising materials. These included television public service announcements, as well as posters, radio, newspaper and magazine advertisements, which were offered free to all broadcast and print media in the United States. Webber was executive producer and wrote a number of the television and radio spots.
Throughout his life Webber pursued fiction writing in his spare time, eventually publishing four novels: The Years of Eden (Boston: Little, Brown, 1951), The Far Shore (Boston: Little, Brown, 1954), What End But Love (Boston: Little, Brown, 1959), and The Great Buffalo Hotel (Boston: Little, Brown, 1979). He also published a book detailing the history of the Benton & Bowles corporation: Our kind of people: the story of the first 50 years at Benton & Bowles (New York: Benton & Bowles, 1979). In the 1980's, Webber attempted unsuccessfully to find a publisher for what would be his final novel, Stepping Stones (originally called Adios, Kalamazoo). He also wrote poetry and short stories throughout his life. Webber was diagnosed with myelogenous leukemia in 1983 and died in 1986 at Montauk, NY.
The Webber papers, dating from 1936-1986, are organized into four series: Personal/Biographical, Writings, Anti-Vietnam War Activism, and Audio-visual Materials. The collection displays the broad creative nature of Webber's life and career, documenting his involvement in both radio and television broadcasting and advertising, his experience as a novelist and writer, as a sailor in World War II, and his activism against the Vietnam War in the early 1970's. As such, they also contain a wealth of information on the advertising industry itself and its response to the Vietnam War, the experience of American novelists in the 20th century, and support research on 20th century American literature. Correspondence can be found scattered throughout the collection: organized chronologically in the Personal/Biographical series, and associated with relevant projects in the Writings and Anti-War series.
Subjects:
Authors, American.; Radio broadcasting--United States.; Television broadcasting--United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Advertisements.; Broadcasting.; Kerry, John.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Webber, Gordon.
Contributors:
Mann, Herbie, 1930-2003.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical Materials
  The Personal/Biographical files contain correspondence and miscellaneous personal materials, including photographs. Webber's correspondence from 1939-1960 primarily documents his professional activities, both at NBC and at Benton & Bowles, though they also relate to his private writing projects. There is one correspondence folder that contains a few letters to and from members of Webber's family, which Webber may have gathered in preparation for writing his autobiography. Gordon Webber served on the cinema jury at the 11th annual International Advertising Film Festival in Venice in 1964, and materials from this trip are collected here. Also in this series are materials from Gordon Webber Day, which was held in Linden, Michigan on June 23, 1985. This folder includes photographs taken on Gordon Webber day, of locals and of Webber himself.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1946-1960 undated (Box 1)
    - Answers to critical mail 1938, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous family letters (Box 1)
  - Autobiographies
    - "Notes for an Autobiography" (Box 1)
    - "Saving My Life: An American Memoir" (notes) (Box 1)
  - Diary
    - European trip 1964 (Box 1)
    - European trip (excerpt) June 1971: "Florence and Surrounding Hill Towns" (Box 1)
  - "Gordon Webber Day" (Linden, MI) materials 1985 (Box 1)
    (include photographs)
  - International Advertising Film Festival, Venice 1964 (Box 1)
  - Linden High School Alumni Banquet Speech June 9, 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Log of the Sea Drifter" November 8-15, 1968 (Box 1)
    (bareboating in the Caribbean)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - News clippings (TV and Radio programs) (Box 1)
  - U.S. Naval Service (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - U.S. Naval Service (scripts) (Box 1)
- Writings
  The Writings series is organized into several subseries: Articles, Speeches/Talks, Radio Scripts, Television Scripts, Film Scripts, Novels, Short Stories, and Miscellaneous.
  - Articles
    The Articles subseries contains articles written by Webber for the newspaper Michigan Journalist while he was a student at Michigan, as well as other miscellaneous articles. The Speeches/Talks subseries includes scripts for Webber's talks on a number of topics, including color television and television advertising. Webber also taught a Corporate Writing Workshop in 1975-1976, and notes for each of his eleven lectures are included here.
    - Michigan Journalist clippings, 1936 (Box 1)
    - New Yorker articles (including cartoon), 1939 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Unpublished articles (Box 1)
  - Speeches/Talks
    The Speeches/Talks subseries includes scripts for Webber's talks on a number of topics, including color television and television advertising. Webber also taught a Corporate Writing Workshop in 1975-1976, and notes for each of his eleven lectures are included here.
    - Color television 1965-1967, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Corporate Writing Workshop lectures 1975-1976, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Federal Trade Commission 1971 (Box 1)
    - Talks at Literary Panels (Box 1)
    - Television advertising
      - 1964, 1967, 1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Radio scripts
    The Radio Scripts subseries contains scripts written by Webber when he worked for NBC and Benton and Bowles in the 1930's and 1940's. Webber was a writer for the program "The Fire Fighters," a children's syndicated radio series, from 1946-1948, and "Reflections," an NBC radio series from 1946-1950, and there are many scripts from these programs represented in this series.
    - Script ideas (Box 1)
    - Commercials (Box 1)
    - "Adventures in Reading" 1938 (Box 1)
    - "Album of Roosevelt Speeches" 1946 (Box 1)
    - American Legion Auxiliary script 1942 (Box 1)
    - "And Golden was the World" 1940 (Box 1)
    - "The Crazy Heart Blues" 1940 (Box 1)
    - "Death of a Heart" 1939 (Box 1)
    - "Defense of the Land" (Box 1)
    - "The Fire Fighters"
      - Scripts, 6 folders (Box 1)
      - Scripts, 18 folders (Box 2)
      - Outlines/summaries (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - "Firefighters News" (Box 2)
    - "The Gift of the Magi" (Box 2)
    - "Going Home" 1939, 1940 (Box 2)
    - "The Immortal Muggsy Morgan" 1942 (Box 2)
    - "Key to a Murder" 1948 (Box 2)
    - "Life is Made for Living" 1940 (Box 2)
    - "Life's Hungry Man" 1940 (Box 2)
    - "The Long Lost Brother of Pinky Chance" 1940 (Box 2)
    - "Mr. Smith's America" (prospectus) (Box 2)
    - "My Town" 1947 (Box 2)
    - "Notes on a Homecoming" (Box 2)
    - "Nothing But the Night" (Box 2)
    - "Old Em's Kentucky Home" (Damon Runyan Theatre) 1948 (Box 2)
    - "The People's Peace" 1939 (Box 2)
    - "Peter's Lovely Pigeons" (scripts and correspondence) 1940 (Box 2)
    - "Reflections"
      - Scripts, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Printed material (Box 3)
    - "Revolt on Humphrey Street" (Box 3)
    - "The Sagamores of Saddle Creek" (Box 3)
    - "The Story Behind the Star Spangled Banner" (Box 3)
    - "Watchman, What of the Night?" (Box 3)
    - NBC scripts and ideas (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous radio scripts, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Television scripts
    The Television Scripts subseries primarily contains a wealth of material on the popular television series "I Remember Mama," including scripts, correspondence and photographs.
    - Script ideas (Box 3)
    - Television advertising, miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - "I Remember Mama"
      - Outlines/summaries, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Scripts 1952-1956, 6 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellanea (Box 3)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - "The Long Lost Brother of Pinky Chance" 1949 (Box 3)
    - NBC-Olds Newsreels 1948 (Box 3)
    - "A Woman on the Case" (outline) (Box 3)
    - "Sixteen" (treatment) 1955 (Box 3)
  - Film scripts
    The Film Scripts subseries contains photo stills, scripts and correspondence from "The Jogger," a short film that Webber wrote and directed with Ernest Garthwaite, and in which he stars (as the jogger). "The Jogger" was awarded the CINE Golden Eagle and Edinburgh Film Festival Certificate in 1971. Also in this subseries is the script for "Stalking the Wild Cranberry: The Making of a TV Commercial" which was a 14 minute documentary that Webber produced for the American Association of Advertising in 1974.
    - "The Alliance of Blue-Fingered Men" (treatment for feature film) (Box 3)
    - "Gus, the Frustrated Bus" 1956 (Box 3)
      35mm film for the American Transit Association
    - "The Jogger" 1971
      - Script (Box 3)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Photographs (Box 3)
    - "Philadelphia Welcomes the GOP", Newsreel 1948 (Box 3)
    - "Stalking the Wild Cranberry: The Making of a TV Commercial" 1974 (Box 3)
  - Novels
    The Novels subseries includes manuscripts, correspondence, and miscellaneous material for all four of Webber's published novels: The Years of Eden (1951), The Far Shore (1954) What End But Love (1959), and The Great Buffalo Hotel (1979). Also included are manuscripts and correspondence related to an unpublished long work of Webber's, titled Stepping Stones (originally titled Adios, Kalamazoo).
    - Reviews (Box 4)
    - Years of Eden (previously The Jungle Years)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Drafts (Box 4)
      - Musical (treatment) (Box 4)
      - Manuscript (Box 4)
    - The Far Shore
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Manuscripts, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - Published editions
        - United States editions (Box 4)
        - Great Britain edition (Box 4)
    - What End But Love
      - Manuscript (Box 5)
      - Film treatment (Box 5)
    - The Great Buffalo Hotel
      - Manuscript, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Film project (Box 5)
      - Russian edition (Box 5)
    - Stepping Stones (previously Adios Kalamazoo)
      - Adios Kalamazoo: Manuscript, 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Adios Kalamazoo: Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Stepping Stones: Draft (Box 6)
      - Stepping Stones: Manuscript, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Short Stories
    The shorter works in the Short Stories subseries include both published and unpublished works. Some of the stories eventually found their way into later novels.
    - "The 1926 Packard Limousine" 1986 (Box 6)
    - "All the Great Elms are Dying" (Box 6)
    - "The Birthday Man" (Box 6)
    - "The Dark Helen" 1950 (Box 6)
      (chapter from Years of Eden, published in Mademoiselle magazine)
    - "The Haunted Barn" 1986 (Box 6)
    - "The Indian Wars on Oak Street" (Box 6)
    - "The Kite That Flew Away" (Box 6)
    - "The Lost Boy" (Box 6)
    - "Menage a Trois -- Plus One?" (Box 6)
    - "The Smiling Boy" (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous short stories (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    The Miscellaneous writings include poetry, a song, treatments for novels, and a notebook containing ideas and characters for an unnamed longer work, titled, "Project X."
    - "The Cowboy's Last Will" (song) (Box 6)
    - Poetry, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "Project X" (Box 6)
    - Treatments for novels
      - The Journey of Julian Starr (Box 6)
      - Memo to Limbo (Box 6)
      - The Redemption of Richard Nixon 1982 (Box 6)
      - The Reunion (Box 6)
- Anti-Vietnam War activism
  The Anti-Vietnam War Activism files contain materials related to Webber's work with the amendment to End the War Committee, notably the television special he produced for the committee, "The Endless War." Also included is material from Webber's involvement in the "Unsell the War" campaign and a "U.S. in Mourning" black armband he designed for an Anti-Vietnam War demonstration.
  - Amendment to End the War Committee
    - Amendment to End the War, general (Box 6)
    - "The Endless War" television special 1970
      - Papers, 7 folders (Box 6)
        (includes scripts, notes, correspondence, and clippings)
      - Budget (Box 6)
  - Corporate Executives Committee for Peace 1970, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Unsell the War campaign 1971
    - Correspondence, 6 folders (Box 7)
      (includes clippings)
    - Unsell Conference. Yale University April 3, 1971 (Box 7)
    - Television advertisement scripts (Box 7)
    - Media requests (Box 7)
    - Print advertisements (Benton and Bowles) (Box 7)
    - Poster (Box 7)
  - "U.S. in Mourning" armband (Box 7)
    (designed by Webber for Anti-Vietnam War demonstration)
- Audio-visual Materials
  The Audio-visual materials series contains five television commercials for Unsell the War. The subjects in the commercials include Robert Muller, former Marine lieutenant, permanently disabled and in a wheelchair, and John Kerry, former U.S. Navy lieutenant and leader of the Vietnam Veterans Against the War. Kerry, who went on to become a United States Senator from Massachusetts and Democratic Presidential nominee for the 2004 election, repeats part of his remarks in 1971 before the United States Senate's Committee on Foreign Relations: "How do you ask a man to be the last to die in Vietnam?...How do you ask a man to be the last to die for a mistake?" Another television advertisement from this series produced by Webber, "Pie Blow-Up" was the winner of a Cork Film Festival Diploma. Also included are audio tapes from "The Endless War" television special, and a copy of the short films "The Jogger" and "Stalking the Wild Cranberry." A separate audio recording for "The Girl with the Swinging Hair," a TV jingle written by Webber for Prell Concentrate (based on an idea supplied by Webber's oldest daughter, Jacqueline Webber, in 1965) is stored in the Bentley's Record Collection.
  - Magnetic audio tracks of the "Endless War" documentary, 2 tapes (Box 8)
  - Films
    - "The Jogger" 1971 (Box 8)
      16 mm. written and directed with Ernest Garthwaite. Gordon Webber is the jogger. Awarded Cine Golden Eagle and Edinburgh Film Festival Certificate
    - "Stalking the Wild Cranberry: The Making of a TV Commercial", 1 reels (Box 8)
      Film written and directed by Gordon Webber
    - "Unsell the War" TV spots, 5 reels
      - "Robert Muller", 30 seconds (Box 8)
      - "John Kerry", 60 seconds (Box 8)
      - "Pie Blowup", 60 seconds (Box 8)
      - "Birthday Helmet", 20 seconds (Box 8)
      - "Little Boy (with flag)", 30 seconds (Box 8)
    - "The Endless War", 1 7 inch film reel; 16 mm. sound reel color (Box 8)
      The film was produced August 1970 and broadcast September 1970 by the Amendment to End the War Committee
  - "Girl with the Swinging Hair" TV jingle 1965 (Box 1)
    (written by Gordon Webber for Prell Concentrate. Based on idea supplied by oldest daughter, Jacqueline Webber)